hey guys in this crash course we're
going to take a look at git now by no
means is this a complete in-depth course
where we're going to go over every
command in every situation this is meant
to be a no nonsense guide for beginners
so either new or intermediate
programmers or developers that either
don't know what git is or have used it
briefly but still don't really grasp the
full concept alright so we're going to
start out with a couple slides and then
we'll jump in and we'll look at some of
the most important commands for you to
know all right so let's talk about what
git is it's a version control system for
tracking changes in computer files all
right so it was initially created in
2005 by Linus Torvalds who was also the
creator of Linux there's no specific
language or framework or anything that
you need to use git you can use it for
static HTML web sites no js' apps Python
Java c-sharp anything at all it just
stores files so git is a distributed
version control system or decentralized
version control system and what that
means is that many developers can work
on a single project without having to be
on the same network
okay so there's also version control
systems that developers actually need to
be on the same network to use that's not
what git is distributed or decentralized
okay get coordinates work between
multiple developers and attracts every
single version and every single change
that's made on the system or on the in
the project you can also revert back to
specific versions of any file at any
time as long as it was committed to the
repository usually when you use git
you'll have a repository on your local
machine that you work on you make
changes and then you upload it to or you
push it to a remote repository okay so
something like github or bitbucket and
then you can push you can push your
local repository to the remote one you
don't need an internet connection to
work on a repository locally and you can
make changes but if you want to push it
the remote repository you will need an
internet connection all right so let's
quickly look at some of the concepts of
git so it essentially keeps track of
your code history with snapshots of your
files alright so you make these
snapshots by making a commitment amande
and you can always go back to see any
snapshot of previously written code and
like I said you can always revert back
if you need to so your code is extremely
safe when you're working with git you
can put your code in a staging area
before actually doing the commit and
writing to the snapshot this is done
with a simple add command ok and I'll go
over all the important commands once you
make a commit to a remote repository
other developers can then pull that
information onto their machines ok so
you can create you can also create
branches but we'll get into that in a
little bit all right I'm trying to just
really stick to the basics here ok so
let's look at the basic commands that
you'll need to learn so get in it will
initialize a git repository so you go
into a folder via your command line or
terminal and you do get an it and it
will create a dot git folder in that in
that project ok and it's hidden by
default you almost never need to go into
this folder at least I never have
alright and then once you initialize
that folder as a repository you can then
start to run other commands all right so
get add we'll add the file or files that
you specify to the staging area or the
index and they'll then be ready for
commit you can run this command as many
times as you need to before committing
and it'll just keep the files in that
staging area so if you want to see what
you have in the staging area and ready
for commit you can just use git status
and that will display paths that have
display the differences between the
working tree and then the staging area
or the index all right so when you're
ready you can go ahead and commit your
files so you run git commit and I'll
take everything that's in the index of
the state
aging area and put it into the local
repository there's also some important
flags that you need to know are options
that you need to know with get commit
but I'll get into those a little later
all right so the next three commands
that I'm going to show you have to do
with remote repositories so if you're
working with github or bitbucket
something like that okay so get push
will take you a local repository that
you've created and then push it to a
remote repository such as github you
will have to add for instance github or
another remote service you'll have to
add that and you have to add your
credentials so it'll ask for your
password and so on you can also create
SSH keys with github so that you don't
have to add passwords or anything like
that so if you want to pull the latest
changes from a remote repository you can
just do get pull all right so if someone
makes a change and you want the latest
version you can use pulp
use the poll come in and then get cloned
will copy a remote repository into your
current folder so if you find a program
or a project or module that you like on
github you can simply clone it and
that'll download a TM machine so
installing it is pretty easy no matter
what system you're using if you're using
Linux it's a simple package command for
Debian use apt-get for fedora use yum
and if you're on a Mac you can go to
this URL right here this get SCM and you
can download it I believe you can also
use homebrewer or some package manager
or something like that
and then for Windows there's a few
different programs you can use but I'd
always suggest this get - fcm comm you
can download the Installer and you can
set it up really easily so this also
comes with a tool called git bash which
is a command line tool and it gives you
a more Linux the environment on Windows
I almost always use that tool over the
standard Windows command line now that
there is graphical tools that you can
use where you don't need to use commands
but I would strongly recommend
then they use the commands because if
you only use the GUI GUI you're not
really learning anything you're not
really learning how git works under the
hood and if you end up somewhere where
you don't have that tool you're going to
be lost and it's not like it's really
hard if it was if it was really
difficult then maybe I'd say I'll use
that but it's not hard at all alright at
least for the basics it can get
complicated to really really know how it
works internally but for things that
you're going to need it for most likely
you're not going to need to know
everything ok that's pretty simple all
right so that's going to be it for the
slides let's go ahead and jump in and I
will show you how it works
all right so we're going to go ahead and
get started and install git now I'm in
Windows if you're on Windows or Mac you
want to go to get - SCM comm and if
you're on a Mac you can click on this
link right down here and that'll take
you to the download page for our Mac for
OSX but we're going to go ahead and
click download on Windows and that's
going to start the download and again if
you're on Linux you can use your app get
or your yum package manager whatever it
is you use ok so let's go ahead and open
this up and click yes so it's just a
winged standard Windows installer we're
just going to click through Program
Files is where it'll be stored you
choose the default for those now this
option here I always choose the last one
which is you get an optional UNIX tools
from the Windows command prompt so it
just gives us some extra commands to use
so I always choose that option and then
the rest of these line ending
conversions I'll just leave the default
terminal emulator we'll just use that
default and we'll keep an able
filesystem caching credential manager
that's fine and that's that's good ok we
don't want to use this experimental tool
so click install and it will install it
on your system
okay so once that's done we're going to
uncheck fully release notes and what's
to watch get - okay click finish and
then this is the git bash tool that they
give you so I would definitely suggest
using this over the standard Windows
command line so now if we say get - -
version you'll see the version you have
yours may be different and then you can
also use this from within the standard
coming in line so if we go CMD and we
open up the Windows command line and -
get - - version it should also work okay
so you can use git from either one now
what I'm going to do is create a project
so let's see on my desktop I'm going to
create a new folder and just going to
call this my app what we put in here
doesn't really matter so when you have
git bash you can also go ahead and
right-click and do git bash here and
that will open up a window there as well
all right so I'll just use this one and
you can hold ctrl and scroll and you can
make this bigger or smaller which is
nice okay so what we want to do first
let's open this up as well kind of have
both of these open at the same time okay
so what I want to do is just create a
couple files that that our project would
have so let's say touch index dot HTML
or you could use your file manager and
let's create an app dot jas okay so we
have these two files that this is our
application and what we want to do is
let's open up and open up atom which is
the text editor that I'm using okay and
we'll move this over here and I'm just
going to add that folder as a project
so desktop my app and let's close this
stuff up and let's just open up
index.html and we'll just put you know
standard HTML tags in here put a title
and body I'll just say this is my app
okay we'll save that and now what I want
to do is I want to initialize this
folder as a git repository so to do that
we just want to say get in it okay for
initialize now once we do that it's
going to create a dot git folder in your
thoughtful in your directory now we
can't see it here because I'm on a new
Windows installation and I don't have
hidden files enabled so what you want to
do is if you're not seeing it here is go
to view options and then change folder
search options go to view and then show
hidden files I'm also going to uncheck
hide extensions for known file types
because I want the extension to be shown
all the time so let's say apply okay and
now you'll see there's a dot git folder
now this stuff in here don't worry about
that at all that's just the gif files I
don't even know what half this stuff
means so we're not going to look into
that there's no reason to so now we have
this initialized as a git repository so
we can start to use git commands now one
thing you should do before you before
you start anything is you want to add
your name and email address to get so to
do that use the config command so get
config - - global and then we're going
to do user dot name user dot name and
then in quotes just put your name okay
and then we're going to do the same
thing for the email so we'll just change
name right here to email
and then just put in your email okay so
now that that's set up let's go ahead
and let's create our let's add the
index.html file to our git repository so
to do that we can say git add and then
index dot HTML all right so it doesn't
tell us anything when we do that but if
we want to check to see what's in the
staging area we can do git status
it's the command we're going to use
quite a bit and what this is telling us
is that the index file has changes to be
committed and that we've added it to the
staging area and then app J s is a file
that's untracked okay so it's telling us
to add it so if you want to remove for
instance index.html from the staging
area you can do get RM so let's go ahead
and do that so if we say get RM and we
want to add the - - cached
option and then index dot HTML okay and
now if we do get status you'll see that
both files are now on tracked now
there's different ways you can add files
for instance we could say get add and we
could use a star or asterisk and say dot
HTML and what that will do is it will
add any any HTML files to the staging
area so now if we say get status you'll
see that it added the index file it also
would have added any other HTML files
that we had alright so I'm going to go
ahead and take the index out again with
the RM command and then I'm going to
show you how to add everything ok so if
you want to add every file you can say
get get pad dot and now if we say get
status you'll see that both the index
and the app file are in the staging area
ok so we haven't committed them yet and
what I want to do is edit one of these
files so we'll go over to index.html and
I'm just going to put in an exclamation
here and then save
and then if we go and we say get status
you can see we now have this changes
notch Stage four commit index.html so
this means that we have changed we've
added some kind of change in the file
while it was in the staging area so it's
telling us to go ahead and add it so get
add all again and then get status and
now you can see that it's back in the
staging area all right so now we're
going to do a commit so for that we say
git commit now there's an option that I
would always suggest you use but I'm
going to show you without it first
so if we say git commit it's going to go
ahead and open up this vim editor which
can be a little confusing because if you
start to type it's not going to do
anything what you need to do is click I
to go into insert mode and now I can
type okay so I'm just going to say
initial commit actually I'll just go
uncomment it down here these some number
signs are basically comments okay so
anything that has the number sign in
front of it is treated as a comment
so I'll just going to remove it from
this initial commit and that gives us a
comment of initial commit okay now to
get out of this we want to do escape
which takes us out of insert mode and
then we want to type in : WQ and enter
and now you'll see that those files have
been committed and it tells us how many
files have changed and gives us the file
names okay so that's how you do a commit
so if we were now to say get status it
says nothing to commit because we've
already committed all of our changes if
we were to go edit a file now and do get
status it'll show us again which files
are in staging and which files are
unchanged all right so let's go ahead
and edit the app.js file I'm just going
to do console dot log and we'll just say
hello save it so now we do lots of slow
slow machine
get status so that's been modified app J
s now I'm going to go ahead and add it
with get add all alright now I want to
do a commit but I want to show you how
we can skip that whole edit stage so we
can say get commit and then add dash M
and then do a comment here so we'll say
changed changed fjs and enter okay so
now it's made that commit and it's
skipped that whole editing stage we just
included the comment within that command
okay using dash M all right so now what
I want to do when we clear this out I
want to show you how to use git ignore
so this is a file that we can include
the files or folders that we don't want
to include in our repository at all so
even if we do get add dot where it adds
everything it's not going to add that so
let's create it
we'll say touch dot to get ignore now if
you try to create this file in Windows
in the file manager you probably won't
be able to because it starts with a dot
so it's going to look at it as an empty
name so either do our touch touch
command or you can create it inside of
an editor I believe all right so what we
want to do is open up get ignore and
we're also going to create a file that
we wouldn't want to include so let's say
let's say touch and create a log dot
text usually you don't want to include
log files so let's add something to this
we'll just say there are logs and save
that and what's going to get ignore and
we'll say log dot txt and save that's
all you have to do is add the file name
now if we go over here and we say get
add all and then get status you can see
the only file that's in the staging
that's change does get ignored normally
log text would be there because we just
changed it but since we added it to get
ignore it's not going to get added okay
you can also add entire directories so
let's say we have will say der one man
this is slow
and let's do jar - and inside these I'm
just going to create let's say new file
and app 1jf let's see inside there -
we'll create a file called app 2jf and
we'll just add something to those okay
we just put that I'll copy it and we'll
also put that in app one okay so if we
go to get ignore and let's say that we
don't want dirt to included at all
so we could just put in slash dirt -
okay and save that and let's go over
here and go get add all and then get the
status and notice that only there one is
in there even though there are two has a
file that we change it's not in there
because we added the whole folder to get
ignore all right you could even add you
could say star dot txt and it'll it'll
withdraw all text files okay and there's
other expressions you can do as well I'm
not going to go through all of them it's
all in the documentation but just know
that if you don't want something
included you want to use git ignore or
dot get a car alright so let's close
these out and the last thing I want to
look at before we look into remote
repositories is branches all right so
let's say that you're a developer
working on a project with a bunch of
people and your assign the task of
adding a login okay so you don't want to
start making changes and you know push
to the repository and have the main code
based codebase edit edited and changed
without finishing the praat are the
functionality okay so what you would do
is you could create a branch call
login or whatever and then work in that
branch and you can still commit it and
all that but it's not going to be
committed to the main branch okay which
is called master you can see right here
when we say get status it tells us we're
on the master branch now to create a
branch we can say get branch and let's
just call this my branch I actually will
just call it login all right we'll
pretend we're adding some login
functionality all right now just doing
that doesn't change us to the branch if
I say get status it still tells us that
I didn't commit these changes so let me
just commit these before we go ahead and
switch branches so we'll say git commit
dash M and I'll just say another change
okay so you'll see that got committed to
master because we're not in that Brett
de log in branch so to switch we can say
git checkout and then the name of the
branch okay so now we're in the log in
branch so I'm going to clear that out
and then I'm going to say get a not get
let's go ahead and create a new file
while we're in this branch called log in
dot html' okay so over here let's going
to log in and we'll just say whatever
doesn't matter log in and save and it's
also edit index.html so I'm just going
to add down here I'm just going to say
log in form and save okay and then let's
say get add all and then let's commit it
commit - M and we'll say log in form
okay so now let's go ahead and switch
back now when I do the switch watch the
log in HTML so get checkout master and
now the log in HTML file is
gone and if we look at index.html that
part of it that we edited is also gone
so the reason for that is because that
is that's in the login branch now if we
want to merge that if we finish the
functionality and we're ready to merge
then we can say while we're in the
master get merge
git merge login all right so it's going
to open this editor up so let's do I and
let's see please enter a commit message
to explain why this merge is necessary
so we'll say added login and then we'll
do escape : WQ enter okay so now even
though we're in the master branch we can
now see the log in HTML okay now there's
a lot more to branching and merging if
you want to get more complicated but
this I want to keep this simple
for beginners this is a good chance if
you're working on your own projects that
you won't even use branches alright so
let's go ahead and now work with a
remote repository so I'm going to go to
github alright so I'm going to go ahead
and just sign in if you don't have an
account just create one
it's obviously free okay so what we want
to do is go up to create new new
repository and I'm just going to call
this my Apps example you can call it
whatever you like put a description say
sample app for tutorial okay so you have
the option of public or private
so public anyone can see it you can
choose who can commit private you can
choose who sees it and commits and I
believe private cost money I'm not sure
I've never actually tried to create a
private repository on my account and you
can also choose to initialize it with a
me file if you want I'm just going to
leave that unchecked you can also choose
to add a get ignore which we already
have or a license so let's go ahead and
Creek clicks create repository alright
and then it will take you to that page
which has nothing in it so it's just
giving us this message here and it tells
you exactly what to do okay so you want
to initialize your directory which we've
already done it's telling us to add a
readme but you don't have to but you
probably should especially if it's a
public repository because you want to
add some information on your application
and you want to use dot MD two for it to
be able to display nicely on on the page
K and MD is marked down now telling us
how to make a commit but we don't
actually have to do this stuff what we
want to do is add this repository as a
remote repository if we go over now we
say get remote that will list the remote
repositories which we have none so let's
go and copy this and we'll paste that in
here run it and then let's say get
remote and it'll say Origin so down here
what we want to do is get push and then
- you origin/master
so let's go ahead and do that just copy
this okay and we'll paste that in and
that should push it to that repository
oh yeah okay so we do have to login to
github
it has to validate your credentials
gender sitcom and password okay so now
it's going it's going to push to the
repository to the master branch and
let's reload this and I'll see we have
our files here all right and then down
here it says help people interested in
this repository understand your project
by creating a readme so let's go ahead
and do that we'll say touch readme dot
MD alright and we can open that up which
I click the wrong editor it's going to
open up vs code okay so let's open up
the readme and I'm not going to go
through the syntax of markdown it's
pretty easy if you want to just look at
the documentation but we're going to put
a heading by using a number sign here
and we'll just say my app this is my app
and we'll save it let's go ahead and add
it and then we'll commit say commit and
we want to add - M comment will say
added readme
okay so right now it's on our local
repository we haven't actually pushed it
yet if I reload you'll see it's not
there so now that we've added that as a
remote repository all we have to do is
today get push and it'll push it right
to github okay so now if I reload you'll
see we have the readme file and it's
actually displayed here now if someone
wanted to get this they could just clone
it okay if we go to clone or download
right here they could choose to download
it as a zip or they could clone it using
this
going to go ahead and copy that link and
then let's let's create another folder
and I'll just call it my app - and let's
open up get - here and then what we want
to do is say git clone and we'll just
paste that link in and it's going to
pull everything in now I actually okay
so what it does is it actually creates
the the folder for you my app sample so
it pulls the entire folder in but if we
open that up you can see we have the
entire application here okay and you can
clone anybody's anybody's project as
long as it's public now if you had
multiple developers working on it and
someone else made a change and we want
to go over here back to our original
folder you could just do get pull and
that would pull everything down you can
see everything is up to date okay I
think that's as far as I want to go into
this so we covered all the basics all
the basic commands you need to start
using git I would suggest if you're not
using it at least now start to create
your repositories for your project
create a github account if you don't
have one create the repositories on
github and then push from your local
machine - to the github repository
alright and you don't even have to use
branches and stuff you know you're just
starting out just getting used to it all
you really need to do is add in commits
and push okay so hopefully this just
helped some of you guys I'm sure some of
you already know all this stuff and
hopefully you just used it as a
refresher or whatever alright so that's
it if you enjoyed it please subscribe
leave like leave a comment and I'll see
you next time